<tool id="hisat_PE" name="hisat PE reads" version="1.0.0">
  <description>Hisat mapping, stringtie and ballgown analysis for groups of samples, PE reads</description>
  <command>
/home/oasis/gordon-data/NGS-ann-project-new/NGS-tools/NGS-wf-galaxy-run-yuan.pl NGS-config qc-hisat-stringtie-pe $output
  </command>
  <inputs>
    <param name="ref_file" type="select" label="Please select a reference genome">
      <options from_data_table="hisat2_indexes">
        <filter type="sort_by" column="2" />
      </options>
    </param>
    <repeat name="group1" title="FASTQ file for sample" max="20" default="1" help="You can add up to 20 samples">
        <param name="groups" type="select" label="You can assign sample into groups, e.g. group 1 as case and group 2 as control, we support up to 4 groups">
          <option value="Group1">group 1</option>
          <option value="Group2">group 2</option>
          <option value="Group3">group 3</option>
          <option value="Group4">group 4</option>
        </param>

        <param name="group1_name" size="40" type="text" label="Please enter a unique sample ID" optional="false"/>
        <param name="group1_inputR1" type="data" format="fastq" label="Fastq file R1"/>
        <param name="group1_inputR2" type="data" format="fastq" label="Fastq file R2"/>
    </repeat>

  </inputs>

  <configfiles>
    <configfile name="config_f" filename="NGS-config">
Read PE
Reference $ref_file.fields.path
Samples
#for $i, $s in enumerate( $group1)
${s.groups} ${s.group1_inputR1.file_name} ${s.group1_inputR2.file_name} ${s.group1_name}
#end for
    </configfile>
  </configfiles>

  <outputs>
    <data name="output"        format="html" label="workflow output" from_work_dir="job.html" />
  </outputs>

  <stdio>
    <regex match="error" source='stderr' level='fatal' />
  </stdio>

  <help>
Summary:
This workflow runs hisat reads mapping for up to 4 groups of samples,
merge the assembled with stringtie, and finally compare the groups pairwisely with ballgown in r.
This protocol was described in Pertea et al. Transcript-level expression analysis of RNA-seq experiments
with HISAT, StringTie and Ballgown. Nat Protoc. 2016 11: 1650–1667

Each group can have multiple samples. The input must be paired ended (PE) fastq files for each sample.

For each sample, the workflow run the following process:
    1. QC, the low quality reads will be removed and low quality bases will be trimmed
    2. hisat, high quality reads will be mapped to the selected genome
    3. sort and convert the sam files to bam by samtools
    4. stringtie, assemble the transcripts

For all the samples together, the workflow run:
    1. stringtie, merge the transcripts

For any pair of groups, the workflow run:
    1. stringtie to estimate transcript abundances and create table counts for ballgown
    2. ballgown in r, compare the transcripts between the two groups (e.g. case and control)

Input:
    1. select the reference genome
    2. PE fastq files (2 files) for each sample
       click "add new FASTQ file for sample" to add a new sample
       select a group for the sample and give a unique sample name

Output:
    1. sam file for each sample from hisat, bam file from samtools
    2. gtf for each sample, merged.gtf from stringtie
    3. transcripts_results.csv, genes_results.csv from ballgown

Important notice :
    1. If you have no replicates in the experiment (i.e., you just have one sample / one replicate) you will not be able to do statistical analysis that requires estimating variance in ballgown, so you won't be able to use stattest and please try other pipeline.
    2. You also need to add the index number into the sample names. For example, if you have 2 groups, and each group has 3 replicates. You'd better add 1_ as the prefix for the first sample in the first group, 2_ as the prefix for the second sample in the first group, 3_ for the third sample in the first group, 4_, 5_, 6_ as the prefix for the first, second, third sample in the second group.
    3. This workflow is still in testing process. Please feel free to contact us for any comments or suggestions.
  </help>

  <citations>
    <citation type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2016.095</citation>
  </citations>

</tool>
